Guide to the A. Nees & Co. decorative paper sample books
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
A. Nees & Co. decorative paper sample books
1865-1930
1880-1914
GEN MSS 1465
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
4.5
19 boxes
Nineteen volumes containing circa 44,000 undated samples of decorative papers manufactured by A. Nees & Co., circa 1865-circa 1930, most circa 1880-1914. Voumes contain small samples of marbled, embossed, coated, and other colored and printed papers affixed to pages within printed borders. Samples are identified by numbers in manuscript annotations or printed labels, some also citing paper names or manufacturing techniques. Volumes contain varying samples, with some overlapping content.
A. Nees & Co
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
A. Nees & Co., Aschaffenburg, Germany, a manufacturer of decorated papers, was founded in 1862 by brothers Albert Nees (1836-1874) and Theodor Nees. In 1866 A. Nees & Co. invented Cambricpapier, a colored paper coated with shellac.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Boxes 1-12 and 14-19: Purchased from Antiquariat Banzhaf on the Gift of Frank H. Sommer, Class of 1944, Fund, 2016.
Box 139: Purchased from Susanne Schulz-Falster Rare Books on the Gift of Frank H. Sommer, Class of 1944, Fund, 2017.
Scope and Contents
Nineteen volumes containing circa 44,000 undated samples of decorative papers manufactured by A. Nees & Co., circa 1865-circa 1930, most circa 1880-1914. Volumes contain small samples of marbled, embossed, coated, and other colored and printed papers affixed to pages within printed borders. Samples are identified by numbers in manuscript annotations or printed labels, some also citing paper names or manufacturing techniques. Volumes contain varying samples, with some overlapping content.
Decorative paper -- Germany -- Aschaffenburg; Marbled papers -- Germany -- Aschaffenburg; Paper industry -- Germany -- Aschaffenburg; Aschaffenburg (Germany) -- Economic conditions -- 19th century; Aschaffenburg (Germany) -- Economic conditions -- 20th Century; Colored paper -- Germany -- Aschaffenburg -- 19th century; Colored paper -- Germany -- Aschaffenburg -- 20th Century; Decorated papers -- Germany -- Aschaffenburg -- 19th century; Decorated papers -- Germany -- Aschaffenburg -- 20th Century; Marbled paper -- Germany -- Aschaffenburg -- 19th century; Marbled paper -- Germany -- Aschaffenburg -- 20th Century; Sample books -- Germany -- Aschaffenburg -- 19th century; Sample books -- Germany -- Aschaffenburg -- 20th Century; Nees, Albert, 1836-1874; Nees, Theodor; A. Nees & Co
- Sample books, Series I
  - Sample book, circa 1865 (Box 1)
  - Sample book, circa 1875 (Box 2)
  - Sample book, circa 1880 (Box 3)
  - Sample book, circa 1885 (Box 4)
  - Sample book, circa 1885 (Box 5)
  - Sample book, circa 1890 (Box 6)
  - Sample book, circa 1895 (Box 7)
  - Sample book, circa 1900 (Box 8)
  - Sample book, circa 1900 (Box 9)
  - Sample book, circa 1905 (Box 10)
  - Sample book, circa 1912 (Box 11)
  - Sample book, circa 1914 (Box 12)
  - Sample book, circa 1920 (Box 13)
  - Sample book, circa 1920 (Box 14)
  - Sample book, circa 1920 (Box 15)
  - Sample book, circa 1920 (Box 16)
  - Sample book, circa 1930 (Box 17)
  - Sample book, circa 1930 (Box 18)
  - Sample book, circa 1930 (Box 19)